{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Fundraising for this monument included the creation of 5 million half-dollar coins that depicted two chatting soldiers on horseback. North Carolina governor Angus McLean offered protection from extradition to Gutzon Borglum, who fled arrest in 1925 after being fired from the design of this monument and destroying his models. This monument, the world’s largest bas relief, is the centerpiece of a park that opened on the 100th anniversary of Abraham Lincoln’s assassination. For ten points, name this controversial Georgia monument that honors three Confederate leaders.",
      "answer": "Stone Mountain"
    },
    {
      "question": "A politician from this state was labeled “eccentric and unpredictable” by Isaiah Berlin because he founded his state’s Progressive Party and yet was a staunch isolationist. Another politician from this state created a short-lived Progressive Party to support his bid for the 1924 Presidential election. While campaigning on the Bull Moose ticket, itself a Progressive Party, Theodore Roosevelt was shot in this state by John Schrank. For ten points, name this state where the progressive La Follette family governed from Madison.",
      "answer": "Wisconsin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country’s national dish consists of a mix of chili peppers and cheese called Ema datshi. In the Battle of the Five Lamas, invaders were blown up while trying to loot this country’s Simtokha Dzong. This country, which banned climbing its mountain Gangkhar Puensum, was led until 2006 by King Jigme Singye Wangchuck, who coined the term Gross National Happiness. Druk the Thunder Dragon is featured on the flag of, for ten points, what Himalayan nation ruled from Thimphu?",
      "answer": "Kingdom of Bhutan or Druk Yul"
    },
    {
      "question": "Joseph Rosa is considered the chief biographer of this man, who allegedly killed a bear with a knife to allow a freight train to continue its journey to Santa Fe. This man killed the leader of the McCanles Gang during a fight at a Pony Express Station. Hays and Abilene were the Kansas cities where this man served as marshal. Jack McCall murdered this man at a saloon in Deadwood while he held two black eights and two black aces during a game of poker. For ten points, name this Wild West folk hero known for carrying the “dead man’s hand.”",
      "answer": "James Butler “Wild Bill” Hickok"
    },
    {
      "question": "Poet Christine de Pisan used this art form to show Reason, Justice, and Rectitude as crown-wearing women building a wall in The Book of the City of Women. The earliest depiction of Thomas Beckett’s murder is one of these works, which are characterized by marginalia and vibrant initials interspersed throughout the text. For ten points, name these medieval books filled with gold and silver embellishments and illustrations.",
      "answer": [
        "illuminated manuscript",
        "word forms like illumination"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization faced a rebellion of miners led by the nobleman Engelbrekt, who called the first Riksdag of all four estates to rally opposition. The members of this organization were unified in their opposition to Albrecht of Mecklenburg, though they later allowed his son Erik of Pomerania to rule over this group. This union was formed in order to counteract the Hanseatic League by Margaret I. For ten points, name this union of Denmark, Sweden, and Norway that lasted from 1397 to 1523.",
      "answer": "Kalmar Union"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ali Kolon and Suleiman Nar were taken hostage by this ruler, who had them educated. This ruler succeeded Abu Bakr II, who disappeared while leading a massive expedition to explore the Atlantic. This ruler ordered the construction of the University of Sankore as part of a series of improvements that included the building of mosques in Timbuktu. For ten points, name this leader of the Mali Empire who devalued the price of gold in Egypt during his 1324 pilgrimage to Mecca.",
      "answer": "Mansa Musa I"
    },
    {
      "question": "As Governor of New York, this man signed an act to gradually abolish slavery that, despite stating children of slaves were free, forced them into decades of indentured servitude. In 1795, this man negotiated the removal of British troops from the Northwest Territory with a treaty fixing many of the issues of the earlier Treaty of Paris. With Alexander Hamilton and James Madison, this man wrote the Federalist Papers. For ten points, name this first Chief Justice of the United States.",
      "answer": "John Jay"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country carried out Operation Cerberus to successfully extract its ships from the port of Brest. The Glorious was sunk by a 27,000 yard shot from one of this country’s Scharnhorst-class battleships. At the Battle of the Denmark Strait, the Prince of Wales and Hood were defeated by this country’s Prinz Eugen and Bismarck. For ten points, name this country whose navy attacked Allied shipping using wolf-packs of U-boat ships.",
      "answer": "Nazi Germany"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ameteorologicalagencymonitors59secretlocationsfortheinitialpresenceoftheseitems.Specimens of the Yoshino variety of these organisms have been proven to be genetically identical to each other, making disease a risk. Maps track a namesake “front” of these items, which are produced from trees in the genus Prunus and are appreciated in a custom called hanami. Springtime crowds flock to Japan to see, for ten points, what types of flowers, otherwise known as sakura?",
      "answer": [
        "cherry blossoms",
        "sakura before mentioned"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This work’s printer, Robert Bell, added the phrase “written by an Englishman” without the author’s permission. Royalties from this work were anonymously donated to the Continental Army. One section of this work comments on the absurdity of an island ruling a nation, and another argues that the colonies have enough resources to rival the navy of Great Britain. For ten points, name this pamphlet written in 1776 by Thomas Paine.",
        "answer": "Common Sense"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Common Sense wasn’t Paine’s only pamphlet to be popular in America and controversial in England; British authorities suppressed this three-part pamphlet that championed deism and attacked the divine nature of the Bible.",
        "answer": "The Age of Reason"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Prohibition Party candidate in this election year faced the Portland Rum Riot as mayor. Neal Dow and Greenback Labor candidate James Weaver ran in this year, whose losing major party candidate was known “Thunderbolt of the Army of the Potomac” for his heroism at Gettysburg. The winner of this election year was a compromise candidate for the Half-Breeds and Stalwarts and was succeeded a year later by his running mate, Chester Arthur. For ten points, name this election year in which Winfield Scott Hancock lost to James Garfield.",
        "answer": "U.S. presidential election of 1880"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Garfield was nominated at the 1880 Republican National Convention in this city, which has hosted 14 RNCs and 11 Democratic conventions, including in 1968.",
        "answer": "Chicago"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Through their contact with China, these people introduced the seax shortsword to Western Europe, and they adopted the Alani practice of lengthening of the skull of infants born to noblemen. These people lost the Battle of Nedao, and a coalition of the Visigoths led by King Theoderic and Romans under Flavius Aetius defeated these people at the Battle of Catalaunian Fields in 451 AD. For ten points, name these nomadic people led by the so-called “Scourge of God,” Attila.",
        "answer": "Huns"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This pope, the first of his name, is given credit for negotiating with Attila to end his invasion of Italy in 452.",
        "answer": "Leo the Great or Leo I"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Nine stages of this location were made out of the tail of Cipactli [see-pock-t’lee], according to stories recorded in the Florentine Codex. An alternative to this location was ruled by Tlaloc [t’lal-ok] and populated by those who had been struck by lightning or drowned; another alternative location was the destination of human sacrifices. Mictlan is the name of, for ten points, what location in Aztec myth through which Xolotl [sho-lot’ll] guided souls?",
        "answer": [
          "Aztec underworld",
          "Mictlan before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Florentine Codex was compiled by Bernardino de Sahagun, a friar from this order that is named for a 13th century saint from Assisi.",
        "answer": [
          "Franciscans",
          "Saint Francis of Assisi"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader authorized the use of deadly force over an internal dispute for the cargo ship Altalena. This leader formed the Rafi party, which lost to the Alignment faction of his successor Levi Eshkol. This leader authorized Operation Magic Carpet in order to transport Jews to his country. This leader consolidated the Haganah and Irgun militias to form the IDF in an 1948 war with the Arabs following independence from Britain. For ten points, name this first prime minister of Israel.",
        "answer": "David Ben-Gurion"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Operation Magic Carpet targeted Jews living in, or with heritages from, this country on the Arabian Peninsula. Today, there may be fewer than 100 Jews living in this country, subject to death threats from Houthis.",
        "answer": "Yemen"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man, who worked alongside future US Ambassador to the UN John Danforth in the Missouri state government, decried a “high tech lynching” in 1991. This man, who gained most senior status after the retirement of Anthony Kennedy, is now often considered the farthest right on the political spectrum of the current court. Sexual harassment against Anita Hill did not prevent the confirmation of, for ten points, what justice who assumed Thurgood Marshall’s seat on the Supreme Court and is known for his general silence during arguments?",
        "answer": "Clarence Thomas"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Clarence Thomas’ Supreme Court confirmation hearings were overseen by this Democrat, who was criticized for his handling of Anita Hill’s claims in his position as chair of the Senate Judiciary Committee in 1991.",
        "answer": "Joseph “Joe” Biden"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This story’s postscript warns that “he that runs races with goblin troopers will have rough riding of it.” The tendency of married men to linger about the taverns in this story’s setting give it the nickname Tarry Town. This story’s protagonist rides the horse Gunpowder and competes with the character Brom Bones for the affection of Katrina Van Tassel. For ten points, name this story from The Sketch Book of Geoffrey Crayon featuring a cursed Hessian soldier and the schoolmaster Ichabod Crane, written by Washington Irving.",
        "answer": "The Legend of Sleepy Hollow"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The ghost of this spy supposedly haunts a tree in “The Legend of Sleepy Hollow” near where Ichabod Crane encounters the Headless Horseman. This spy was hanged on October 2, 1780, after having been caught near Tarrytown with six pages of incriminating evidence in his boot.",
        "answer": "John Andr´e"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler’s death was kept secret by Sokollu Mehmed Pasha to maintain troop morale during the siege of Szigetvar. This ruler made peace with Shah Tahmasp of the Safavid Empire in the Peace of Amasya and signed another treaty with Francis I to form an “Unholy Alliance” to check the power of the Habsburgs. Though this man could not conquer Vienna, he was victorious at a 1526 battle in Hungary. For ten points, name the longest reigning Ottoman sultan.",
        "answer": [
          "Suleiman I",
          "Suleiman the Magnificent"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Suleiman won this 1526 battle over Louis II, splitting Hungary between Ottoman and Habsburg rule.",
        "answer": "Battle of Mohacs , but be lenient"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Cuban Missile Crisis",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Soviet leader who sparred with Kennedy during the crisis.",
          "answer": "Nikita Khrushchev"
        },
        {
          "question": "Soviet capital city connected to DC by a special hotline after the crisis.",
          "answer": "Moscow"
        },
        {
          "question": "Number of days the crisis lasted; also the title of Robert Kennedy’s memoir of the crisis.",
          "answer": "Thirteen Days"
        },
        {
          "question": "Burmese diplomat who mediated the crisis as UN Secretary-General.",
          "answer": "U Thant"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of ballistic missile that the Americans secretly dismantled and removed as part of the crisis resolution.",
          "answer": "PGM-19 Jupiter ballistic missiles"
        },
        {
          "question": "Either of the two countries from which those missiles were secretly removed.",
          "answer": "Turkey and/or Italy"
        },
        {
          "question": "American ambassador who demanded “don’t wait for the translation!” in a heated UN Security Council meeting during the crisis.",
          "answer": "Adlai Stevenson II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian submarine officer who refused to authorize a nuclear strike during the crisis, saving the world from nuclear war.",
          "answer": "Vasily Arkhipov"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Terror at the 1972 Olympics",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "German city that hosted the 1972 Olympics.",
          "answer": "Munich"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose Jewish athletes were abducted and killed in the attack.",
          "answer": "Israel"
        },
        {
          "question": "German airline whose Flight 615 was hijacked in October ‘72 to gain the release of three Munich attackers.",
          "answer": "Lufthansa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Militant Palestinian group founded by Salah Khalaf that carried out the attack.",
          "answer": "Black September"
        },
        {
          "question": "Covert operation that assassinated members of that group over the next two decades.",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Wrath of God",
            "Mivtza Za’am Ha’el",
            "Operation Bayonet"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Intelligence agency whose agents retaliated for the attack with that operation.",
          "answer": "Mossad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leftist terror group founded by Baader and Meinhof, two men whose release was demanded by the Munich attackers.",
          "answer": "Red Army Faction"
        },
        {
          "question": "German elite tactical group founded in the wake of the Munich attack.",
          "answer": [
            "GSG 9",
            "Grenzschutzgruppe 9",
            "Border Protection Group 9"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Genghis Khan",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Animal whose Mongol riders used a special compound bow to decimate Genghis’ enemies.",
          "answer": "horse"
        },
        {
          "question": "Portable, round-tent his army used on campaigns.",
          "answer": [
            "yurts",
            "gers"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Indian river where he defeated Jalal al-Din and where a Bronze Age civilization flourished 4,000 years ago.",
          "answer": [
            "Indus River",
            "Indus River Valley Civilization"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Script he adopted for his empire, an old version of a script currently used by a namesake minority Muslim ethnicity in Xinjiang [shin-jee’ahng].",
          "answer": "Uyghur script"
        },
        {
          "question": "Slavic confederation ruled by the Ruriks that he invaded in 1223.",
          "answer": "Kievan Rus’"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who succeeded him as Great Khan, his third son.",
          "answer": "Ogedei Khan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secret law code he issued to control his empire.",
          "answer": "Yassa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Grand Empress, his first wife, whose kidnapping by the Three Merkits may have started his military campaigns.",
          "answer": "Borte"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In negotiations with this man, George Mikan declined to present him with a certified check for one million dollars, costing Mikan his job as commissioner of the ABA. While playing for John Wooden at UCLA, this man converted to (20 pts)",
        "Islam. In 1974, he requested a trade from Milwaukee to a city with a more diverse culture; he landed in Los Angeles, where he won five titles while playing with (10 pts)",
        "Magic Johnson. The “skyhook” was the signature play of, for ten points, what center for the Bucks and Lakers who scored the most points in NBA history?"
      ],
      "answer": "Kareem Abdul-Jabbar or Lew Alcindor"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The losing side in this battle allegedly began to throw oranges and lemons after running out of usable weapons. In this battle, Marcantonio Colonna withstood an attack from Uluc Ali’s fleet in the Gulf of Patras in this battle, which was preceded by a siege of (20 pts)",
        "Famagusta. Author Miguel de Cervantes lost an arm fighting in this battle, the last major battle of (10 pts)",
        "rowing ships. The Real [ray-AHL] served as the flagship of Don Juan of Austria, the winning commander of, for ten points, what 1571 battle, a massive naval defeat for the Ottoman Empire?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Lepanto"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These people, who were the main inhabitants of the Mayu Frontier District, were targeted in Operation King Dragon. These people were armed by the British “V-Force” and fought against pro-Japanese Red Karens. Many of these people have sought asylum at (20 pts)",
        "Cox’s Bazar after a series of 2012 riots led to their mass persecution. These inhabitants of (10 pts)",
        "Rakhine State have been subject to attacks by Theravada Buddhists in their home country. For ten points, name this Muslim ethnic group whose members have sought asylum in Bangladesh after fleeing Burma."
      ],
      "answer": "Rohingya people"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event concluded with Patrick Sarsfield’s retreat at the Battle of Reading [redding]. A successful invasion of Torbay, crucial to the beginning of this event, was followed by support from the (20 pts)",
        "Immortal Seven. Organizers of this event had been angered by the Declaration of Indulgence, which sought to achieve religious tolerance for (10 pts)",
        "Catholics. A “Protestant wind” helped facilitate the crossing of the English Channel during, for ten points, what relatively peaceful revolution in which James II was overthrown by William and Mary as rulers of England?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Glorious Revolution",
        "Revolution of 1688"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man and his sons killed James Doyle, two of Doyle’s sons, and two other men in a May 24th, 1856 attack that was inspired by the sacking of Lawrence a week prior. The (20 pts)",
        "Pottawatomie Massacre was led by this man, who declared that he was “quite certain” that America’s crimes will “never be purged away but with blood” on the morning of his (10 pts)",
        "hanging in 1859. Robert E. Lee led a Marine detachment that ended this man’s brief occupation of a federal armory, which he had hoped would lead to an armed slave uprising. For ten points, name this violent abolitionist who led the raid on Harper’s Ferry."
      ],
      "answer": "John Brown"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1823, Bella Salomon gifted a complete manuscript of one of this composer’s works to Felix Mendelssohn, whose staging of the piece five years later kicked off a (20 pts)",
        "revival of this man’s work. This composer presented a set of six instrumental works to Margrave Christian Ludwig, and a melody by Frederick the Great was used as the basis for this composer’s Musical Offering. This composer’s many (10 pts)",
        "sons included the composers Carl Phillip Emmanuel and Johann Christian. The Brandenburg Concertos were written by, for ten points, what German Baroque composer, the oldest of the “Three B’s”?"
      ],
      "answer": "Johann Sebastian Bach"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event was triggered by an accident involving barrels of benzol. Vince Coleman sent a telegram reading “Hold up the train. [...] Guess this will be my last message. Good-bye boys.”, which saved hundreds of passengers from riding directly into this event. A (20 pts)",
        "half-ton piece of metal that was thrown over 2 miles away is now a monument to this event; that metal was part of the anchor of the SS (10 pts)",
        "Mont Blanc, whose cargo caught fire. For ten points, name this December 6, 1917 tragedy in which over 2,000 people were killed in Nova Scotia in the largest pre-nuclear, man-made explosion in history."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Halifax explosion",
        "descriptions of the SS Mont Blanc explosion before mentioned",
        "“explosion” not needed after mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Supreme Court ruled in Cooper v. Aaron against this city’s plan to wait over two years to implement a proposal by Virgil Blossom. Ronald Davies issued a desegregation order in this city, which led to an iconic photo of (20 pts)",
        "Elizabeth Eckford. This city’s mayor, Woodrow Wilson Mann, sent a telegram asking for federal troops to President (10 pts)",
        "Eisenhower. Governor Orval Faubus tried to thwart the Brown v. Board decision at Central High School in, for ten points, what city where, in 1957, nine black students helped desegregate public schools in Arkansas?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Little Rock",
        "Little Rock Nine"
      ]
    }
  ]
}